<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>seafood-homer</title>
    <description>Blog for mellowed regurgitations of my environment.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 18:26:26 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 18:26:26 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Light</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What have you revealed to me that I did not see for myself,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and what truth have you helped me discern,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which, in your shadow,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;would have been to me an empty surface,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;like a rock held fast by the earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;whose underbelly teems with life,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;hiding the plain forms of being that nourish the soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I come to anger,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;what more than reason can purify my heart&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and sculpt my intentions into the well-being of every person&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for the duration of this brief visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or is all goodness stored as light behind the glass of the sky,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to us, translucent,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in some moments shining over the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 11:20:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/light/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/light/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;That which controls the depths of the sounds and shapes around me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the map of how far along each dimension&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to run the presence of each sensation and object,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;remains hidden and separate from my description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am unable to distill the variation in these forms,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to catalog the shrillness of the bird call,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the sturdiness and angle of the rooftop,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which, though imperfect,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I perceive as a smooth triangle,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;terminating above the yard in a clean line,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;while, simultaneously, forming a point&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from which all else falls,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the water and debris to the ground below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even my boots slide against the red shingles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lift myself higher to see inside the nest,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and peer into the origin of the bird call,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;witnessing the smallness and complexity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sounding the ineffable fullness of life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 11:10:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/nest/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/nest/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Multi-Node Multi-GPU Comprehensive Working Example for PyTorch Lightning on AzureML</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With the permission of my company, OptumLabs, I wrote a comprehensive Medium blog post on multi-node multi-GPU training for PyTorch Lightning on AzureML.  You can check it out at &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@joelstremmel22/multi-node-multi-gpu-comprehensive-working-example-for-pytorch-lightning-on-azureml-bde6abdcd6aa&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;. I hope the guide is useful to ML practitioners and researchers alike.  Feel free to leave comments on Medium.  Thanks in advance for any feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 11:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/machine-learning/multi-node-multi-gpu-comprehensive-working-example-for-pytorch-lightning-on-azureml/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/machine-learning/multi-node-multi-gpu-comprehensive-working-example-for-pytorch-lightning-on-azureml/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Machine-Learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>April</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I listen to the still house,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birds calling in the morning fog,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world swelling in my mind,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking hold of my senses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes incredible willpower to allow these entrances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So often I am pulling threads from myself,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stretching them out over the earth to fill it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And be seen in bright colors, expertly woven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I will be called again to say something,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this morning I make myself empty and become everything,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boundary between myself and the world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like a kitchen doorway on a hinge,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freely opening and closing to mingle the smells&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And allow the meal to be prepared and delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Apr 2021 05:50:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/april/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/april/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Perfectum</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Click the thumbnail below to view “Perfectum” on YouTube.  I’m considering creating more short films and would appreciate any feedback in the YouTube comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8xQsOL5TjwE&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/8xQsOL5TjwE/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Perfectum (2021) Short Film&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 12:30:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/perfectum/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/perfectum/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Film</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deaf Patron: Seattle Fall 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Start the engine,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said the mechanic without words&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in two languages,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first known to most who speak,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second to few,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save the man to whom he gestured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man signed back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the street from the auto shop&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is short cut grass,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picnic tables, and sunshine,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beating down on the corporate art,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The giant copper people embracing,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their legs towering over me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their shadows cast far out into the street,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost touching the embers of the trees,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still glowing orange around the edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a giant hole through the middle of the people through which the rare blue sky is visible,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through which the bay, and the train tracks, and the occasional rushing Sounder can be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no telling to whom the hole belongs,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To each body or to the space between bodies,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shape they make, curved, leaning against each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no description for this piece,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No sign revealing the work beyond that of the bodies, and their heads,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Split wide open at the top like flower petals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If sprinklers rise up from their skulls&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And proceed to water the tidy grass before the office buildings with no employees,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will join in the drinking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 22:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/seattle-fall-2020/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/seattle-fall-2020/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Badlands (1973)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eITb-5R76TU&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/eITb-5R76TU/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Badlands (1973) Trailer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I was thinking back to some of the films I watched in college.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_World_(2005_film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Terrence Malick stuck out in my mind.  I recall my friend sharing that Malick took years to plan his films.  Indeed, he has been directing for years but has released few movies over his long career (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terrence_Malick#Filmography&quot;&gt;Malick’s filmography here&lt;/a&gt;), especially given his success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that superficial attributes of a person prompt us to assume a hidden depth to their words and work.  Malick is no exception.  With his degree in Philosophy from Harvard, I am quick to assume that his time between films is spent brooding over the implications of each shot and detail.  But at first glance, nothing about &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; struck me as philosophical.  It was Martin Sheen in a white T-shirt and jean jacket that captured my attention, a handsome man in his prime, a James Dean not of Hollywood but South Dakota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, without having seen many of his movies (and he has far more than Malick) Martin Sheen is someone I like.  I owe this to Krista Tippett (to whom I owe much) who interviewed Sheen in 2017 on her podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://onbeing.org/programs/martin-sheen-spirituality-of-imagination-jun2017/&quot;&gt;On Being&lt;/a&gt;.  There, Sheen mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brothers_Karamazov&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Brothers Karamazov&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a book that changed his life.  It is a book my Existentialism professor in college recommended as his all-time favorite, but it was Sheen’s glowing review that convinced me to read it.  A few years later, I am slightly embarrassed that all I have to mention from the tome is the same quote you’ll find all over the internet, that “without God, everything is permitted.”  Nonetheless, it may be this quote that best characterizes &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; Malick takes many liberties with the true story of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Starkweather&quot;&gt;Charles Starkweather&lt;/a&gt;.  From Nebraska, not South Dakota, Starkweather was only 19 when he murdered 11 people.  Malick casts Sheen as 25-year-old Kit Carruthers, though Sheen was actually 33 at the time, with a physique far better than what you might imagine for an outcast serial killer.  Kit’s magnetism and Malick’s shots of the wide-open South Dakota prairie defy expectations throughout the film.  It’s not a dark, twisted psychological thriller like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zAGVQLHvwOY&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from 2019, which though an impressive performance from Joaquin Phoenix, was disturbing in the ways one might expect.  Kit Carruthers on the other hand, surprises his audience throughout &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;, holding up innocent victims and pulling the trigger without a second thought, without ever calling his actions into question, all the while bringing his 15-year-old girlfriend, Holly, along for the ride.  It is, for Kit, and for Malick, choreographing Kit’s tear on the silver screen, as if everything is permitted, existing entirely without reason.  In &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;, Kit Carruthers has no schizophrenic parent as does Arthur Fleck, The Joker, to explain his detachment from reality and human suffering.  In fact, there is no back story, only his immediate desire for Holly, his 15-year-old companion, and a life free of authority, neither of which vindicate his character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those, including yours truly, who admire youthful rebellion, the James Deans of the world, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easy_Rider&quot;&gt;Easy Riders&lt;/a&gt; (a favorite worth comparing to &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;), there is nothing to admire about Kit Carruthers.  There is no ambition or idealism offered by his actions or words to put in contention with the commonly accepted values of society, for Kit makes no such contention, and neither does Malick who merely portrays a mind in which everything is permitted, and lays bare the reality of such an attitude on the silver screen, against the backdrop of the golden, South Dakota prairie.  In this way there is nothing to value in Kit’s rebellion, not even freedom, something Kit himself can’t stand.  He allows himself to be caught.  He has no more reason to flee than to be captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a life free from authority is not Kit’s ultimate motive, neither is his love for Holly, particularly if the actions of the real Charles Starkweather may speak for Kit Carruthers.  In his capture, the real Starkweather turned on his girlfriend, insisting she was guilty for the murders he committed.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iir_xAbt-ak&quot;&gt;“Nebraska”&lt;/a&gt;, the Bruce Springsteen song about Starkweather, put a spin on his insistence, claiming that Starkweather wanted Caril Ann Fugate, the real Holly, on his lap when he went to the electric chair on June 25th, 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Starkweather was the last Nebraskan to be sentenced to death until 1994. It was not Malick’s intention for the viewer of &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; to rejoice in the death of Kit Carruthers, or even to lament it, as no doubt many viewers like myself are opposed to the death penalty, no matter the crimes committed.  Instead, Malick cuts Badlands short, sharing that Kit was sentenced to death but ending the film without showing it.  Instead, the film ends with the viewer wondering what to make of the bloody spree of Kit Carruthers, not whether or not his death at the hands of the law is justified.  Similarly, there is little room for the viewer to question if Kit’s murders are justified.  They are simply permitted in his mind, and by Malick who believes there is something worth seeing in the story, which, among other things, is also a beautiful excuse to show off his cinematography.  But it is no mistake that these go hand in hand: the beautiful and the terrible, the commendable and the reprehensible.  There is something so clear about &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; that we wonder if it was necessary to represent, which is perhaps exactly why Malick chose to represent it.  After all, we are made to come to terms with the film.  And perhaps there is something to love in the search for depth where maybe there is none.  Or, there is a very big mistake in the mind that finds no depth, and needs for some things not to be permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 15:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/badlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/badlands/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Film</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Running Beneath the Moon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When the moon rises over the flood lamps on the empty playground,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And flickers between the man-made glow that hides the stars,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that for all that is almost too present and full in its urgency,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an empty cradle, holding my deepest sorrow and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It swells above and below my past and future,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carries me through time, space, and the presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all objects, actions, and consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all I seek to meet and be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pulled and met and held&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the tissue of all that is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself one piece,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You another,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darting through night and day,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through lighted and darkened paths&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the promises of a sovereign mind and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the people grown now,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urging the world forward with the labor of routine and thought,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving a piece of fabric here; tearing another there; reconfiguring an infinitesimal fraction,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are paid even less of the whole, but are whole in the smallness of our dashing shadows,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cast against the light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are held in the night,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the day to follow,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the life begun not long ago,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In play and rest beside each other,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep in the emptiness of everything,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retained in the sky and on the ground,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the ever-reaching ceiling and floor,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nestled very, very close on this scale,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practically the same cosmic point,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contiguous in space and the passage of time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now until the end.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 19:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/running-beneath-the-moon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/running-beneath-the-moon/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Little Creatures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7IMqoztesjFDgyeibke8Jz&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Little Creatures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Talking Heads is a fine album and I highly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 12:03:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/music/little-creatures/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/music/little-creatures/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Music</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pretraining Federated Text Models for Next Word Prediction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the winter of 2020, I completed my MS in data science and my capstone project on pretraining neural networks for federated next word prediction.  The focus of this work was to contribute research to the growing field of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai.googleblog.com/2017/04/federated-learning-collaborative.html&quot;&gt;federated learning&lt;/a&gt;, to which I was introduced during my machine learning course, DATA558 at University of Washington.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.google/people/author35837/&quot;&gt;Brendan McMahan&lt;/a&gt;, a principal researcher in federated learning, gave a guest lecture on his work at Google on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1602.05629&quot;&gt;training federated deep learning models&lt;/a&gt; which introduced me to the topic.  My enterprising classmate and soon to be research partner followed up with Brendan after the lecture.  This led to a project the following academic year in which he and I worked with two project sponsors from the Google federated learning team to conduct research in the field and contribute experimental findings to their ongoing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research focused on pretraining methods for federated deep learning models designed for next word prediction.  This is an important area of applied research for federated learning, as the Google mobile keyboard application uses federated learning to train models to predict words in text messages, offering user suggestions for the top three predicted words given some starting text.  Model pretraining promises enhanced accuracy and reduced training time, which we demonstrate in our research results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Google mobile keyboard is an early application of federated learning, there are many open areas of research, some with tremendous impact potential.  For example, most clinical research with machine learning models is limited to electronic medical records owned by a single institution.  Models may not generalize from training data at one institution to another, and training datasets are often limited to the size of the dataset at one institution.  Federated models present the possibility of learning from medical records from many institutions without compromising privacy or security by bringing the model to each distributed dataset and averaging the learned parameters, as opposed to centrally aggregating patient data, which is often a legal and ethical impossibility. Just as Google uses federated models to avoid centrally aggregating user text messages, so too federated models could be used to generate predictions and recommendations for patients based on distributed medical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to my research partner, mentors on the federated learning team at Google, and professor at UW for the opportunity to get involved in this exciting area of research.  Feel free to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/federated-learning-experiments/fl-text-models&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.04828&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; for our work, and please don’t hesitate to reach out if the topic sparks your interest :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 11:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/machine-learning/pretraining-federated-text-models/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/machine-learning/pretraining-federated-text-models/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Machine-Learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
