<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>seafood-homer</title>
    <description>Blog for mellowed regurgitations of my environment.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 11:19:09 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 11:19:09 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Roots</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent years away from you,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And buried thousands of hours of thoughts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below the surface of your being,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep where I thought you were not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, on a dark day,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a tree-covered path,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed the roots of the trees&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were so strong&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That they rose from below&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And shattered the bricks of the path,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking the seal that held them straight.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 17:30:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/roots/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/roots/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Badlands (1973)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eITb-5R76TU&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/eITb-5R76TU/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Badlands (1973) Trailer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I was thinking back to some of the films I watched in college.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_World_(2005_film)&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The New World&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Terrence Malick stuck out in my mind.  I recall my friend sharing that Malick took years to plan his films.  Indeed, he has been directing for years but has released few movies over his long career (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terrence_Malick#Filmography&quot;&gt;Malick’s filmography here&lt;/a&gt;), especially given his success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that superficial attributes of a person prompt us to assume a hidden depth to their words and work.  Malick is no exception.  With his degree in Philosophy from Harvard, I am quick to assume that his time between films is spent brooding over the implications of each shot and detail.  But at first glance, nothing about &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; struck me as philosophical.  It was Martin Sheen in a white T-shirt and jean jacket that captured my attention, a handsome man in his prime, a James Dean not of Hollywood but South Dakota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, without having seen many of his movies (and he has far more than Malick) Martin Sheen is someone I like.  I owe this to Krista Tippett (to whom I owe much) who interviewed Sheen in 2017 on her podcast, &lt;a href=&quot;https://onbeing.org/programs/martin-sheen-spirituality-of-imagination-jun2017/&quot;&gt;On Being&lt;/a&gt;.  There, Sheen mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brothers_Karamazov&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Brothers Karamazov&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as a book that changed his life.  It is a book my Existentialism professor in college recommended as his all-time favorite, but it was Sheen’s glowing review that convinced me to read it.  A few years later, I am slightly embarrassed that all I have to mention from the tome is the same quote you’ll find all over the internet, that “without God, everything is permitted.”  Nonetheless, it may be this quote that best characterizes &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; Malick takes many liberties with the true story of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Starkweather&quot;&gt;Charles Starkweather&lt;/a&gt;.  From Nebraska, not South Dakota, Starkweather was only 19 when he murdered 11 people.  Malick casts Sheen as 25-year-old Kit Carruthers, though Sheen was actually 33 at the time, with a physique far better than what you might imagine for an outcast serial killer.  Kit’s magnetism and Malick’s shots of the wide-open South Dakota prairie defy expectations throughout the film.  It’s not a dark, twisted psychological thriller like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zAGVQLHvwOY&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from 2019, which though an impressive performance from Joaquin Phoenix, was disturbing in the ways one might expect.  Kit Carruthers on the other hand, surprises his audience throughout &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;, holding up innocent victims and pulling the trigger without a second thought, without ever calling his actions into question, all the while bringing his 15-year-old girlfriend, Holly, along for the ride.  It is, for Kit, and for Malick, choreographing Kit’s tear on the silver screen, as if everything is permitted, existing entirely without reason.  In &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;, Kit Carruthers has no schizophrenic parent as does Arthur Fleck, The Joker, to explain his detachment from reality and human suffering.  In fact, there is no back story, only his immediate desire for Holly, his 15-year-old companion, and a life free of authority, neither of which vindicate his character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even for those, including yours truly, who admire youthful rebellion, the James Deans of the world, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easy_Rider&quot;&gt;Easy Riders&lt;/a&gt; (a favorite worth comparing to &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt;), there is nothing to admire about Kit Carruthers.  There is no ambition or idealism offered by his actions or words to put in contention with the commonly accepted values of society, for Kit makes no such contention, and neither does Malick who merely portrays a mind in which everything is permitted, and lays bare the reality of such an attitude on the silver screen, against the backdrop of the golden, South Dakota prairie.  In this way there is nothing to value in Kit’s rebellion, not even freedom, something Kit himself can’t stand.  He allows himself to be caught.  He has no more reason to flee than to be captured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a life free from authority is not Kit’s ultimate motive, neither is his love for Holly, particularly if the actions of the real Charles Starkweather may speak for Kit Carruthers.  In his capture, the real Starkweather turned on his girlfriend, insisting she was guilty for the murders he committed.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iir_xAbt-ak&quot;&gt;“Nebraska”&lt;/a&gt;, the Bruce Springsteen song about Starkweather, put a spin on his insistence, claiming that Starkweather wanted Caril Ann Fugate, the real Holly, on his lap when he went to the electric chair on June 25th, 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Starkweather was the last Nebraskan to be sentenced to death until 1994. It was not Malick’s intention for the viewer of &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; to rejoice in the death of Kit Carruthers, or even to lament it, as no doubt many viewers like myself are opposed to the death penalty, no matter the crimes committed.  Instead, Malick cuts Badlands short, sharing that Kit was sentenced to death but ending the film without showing it.  Instead, the film ends with the viewer wondering what to make of the bloody spree of Kit Carruthers, not whether or not his death at the hands of the law is justified.  Similarly, there is little room for the viewer to question if Kit’s murders are justified.  They are simply permitted in his mind, and by Malick who believes there is something worth seeing in the story, which, among other things, is also a beautiful excuse to show off his cinematography.  But it is no mistake that these go hand in hand: the beautiful and the terrible, the commendable and the reprehensible.  There is something so clear about &lt;em&gt;Badlands&lt;/em&gt; that we wonder if it was necessary to represent, which is perhaps exactly why Malick chose to represent it.  After all, we are made to come to terms with the film.  And perhaps there is something to love in the search for depth where maybe there is none.  Or, there is a very big mistake in the mind that finds no depth, and needs for some things not to be permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 15:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/badlands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/film/badlands/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Film</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Running Beneath the Moon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When the moon rises over the flood lamps on the empty playground,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And flickers between the man-made glow that hides the stars,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that for all that is almost too present and full in its urgency,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an empty cradle, holding my deepest sorrow and joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It swells above and below my past and future,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carries me through time, space, and the presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all objects, actions, and consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all I seek to meet and be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am pulled and met and held&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the tissue of all that is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself one piece,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You another,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darting through night and day,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through lighted and darkened paths&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the promises of a sovereign mind and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, the people grown now,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Urging the world forward with the labor of routine and thought,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving a piece of fabric here; tearing another there; reconfiguring an infinitesimal fraction,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are paid even less of the whole, but are whole in the smallness of our dashing shadows,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cast against the light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are held in the night,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the day to follow,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the life begun not long ago,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In play and rest beside each other,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep in the emptiness of everything,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retained in the sky and on the ground,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the ever-reaching ceiling and floor,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nestled very, very close on this scale,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practically the same cosmic point,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contiguous in space and the passage of time,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now until the end.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 19:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/running-beneath-the-moon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/running-beneath-the-moon/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Little Creatures</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/album/7IMqoztesjFDgyeibke8Jz&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Little Creatures&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Talking Heads is a fine album and I highly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 12:03:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/music/little-creatures/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/music/little-creatures/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Music</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pretraining Federated Text Models for Next Word Prediction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the winter of 2020, I completed my MS in data science and my capstone project on pretraining neural networks for federated next word prediction.  The focus of this work was to contribute research to the growing field of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai.googleblog.com/2017/04/federated-learning-collaborative.html&quot;&gt;federated learning&lt;/a&gt;, to which I was introduced during my machine learning course, DATA558 at University of Washington.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.google/people/author35837/&quot;&gt;Brendan McMahan&lt;/a&gt;, a principal researcher in federated learning, gave a guest lecture on his work at Google on &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1602.05629&quot;&gt;training federated deep learning models&lt;/a&gt; which introduced me to the topic.  My enterprising classmate and soon to be research partner followed up with Brendan after the lecture.  This led to a project the following academic year in which he and I worked with two project sponsors from the Google federated learning team to conduct research in the field and contribute experimental findings to their ongoing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research focused on pretraining methods for federated deep learning models designed for next word prediction.  This is an important area of applied research for federated learning, as the Google mobile keyboard application uses federated learning to train models to predict words in text messages, offering user suggestions for the top three predicted words given some starting text.  Model pretraining promises enhanced accuracy and reduced training time, which we demonstrate in our research results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Google mobile keyboard is an early application of federated learning, there are many open areas of research, some with tremendous impact potential.  For example, most clinical research with machine learning models is limited to electronic medical records owned by a single institution.  Models may not generalize from training data at one institution to another, and training datasets are often limited to the size of the dataset at one institution.  Federated models present the possibility of learning from medical records from many institutions without compromising privacy or security by bringing the model to each distributed dataset and averaging the learned parameters, as opposed to centrally aggregating patient data, which is often a legal and ethical impossibility. Just as Google uses federated models to avoid centrally aggregating user text messages, so too federated models could be used to generate predictions and recommendations for patients based on distributed medical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m grateful to my research partner, mentors on the federated learning team at Google, and professor at UW for the opportunity to get involved in this exciting area of research.  Feel free to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/federated-learning-experiments/fl-text-models&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.04828&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; for our work, and please don’t hesitate to reach out if the topic sparks your interest :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 11:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/data-science/pretraining-federated-text-models/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/data-science/pretraining-federated-text-models/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Data-Science</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maple Loop Pass</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/seafood-homer/assets/images/maple-loop-pass.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite hikes tend to be colorful, exposed, and nestled between mountains for as far as the eye can see.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/maple-pass&quot;&gt;Maple Loop Pass&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Cascades_National_Park&quot;&gt;North Cascades National Park&lt;/a&gt; is no exception, offering all of these in a seven mile loop which gains 2,000 feet in elevation and carries hikers along a narrow but innocuous ridgeline for much of the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildflowers decorate the vast, exposed fields on either side of the ridgeline, and views of Lake Ann and Rainy Lake offer great places to stop and relax.  If the weather looks promising, the apex of the loop, Maple Pass, is a fine place for a picnic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steady elevation gain and moderate distance make this hike a worthy weekend constitutional, while the open environment offers a gorgeous respite for those seeking peace in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 11:01:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/places/maple-loop-pass/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/places/maple-loop-pass/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Places</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dogs</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;ms&quot;&gt;MS’&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few people in the audience can discern the rhythm. In fact few people on stage are able to so much as tap along, save André Eats and about half the leaderboard. André leads the pack. 40 fish tacos. His cheeks are crimson; his eyes are wide. Nathan’s pace. André’s a taco to hot dog transubstantiation away from fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time stops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How does it feel to set a record on your first appearance?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I just came out here and fought through. I kept my head down. I stuck to what I do best.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;André did doubles best. It was the psychology of it. Sure it was a slower hand to stomach time than a single, but it felt like eating one, one big one, one big one that counted for two. And this time his 23 grabs, 46 tacos, cheese, tartar, and all, brought him 3,760 dollars. The other half went to charity. The one that mailed the bus ticket to San Jose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Babe, I did it :p,” he texted Cara,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Great. I need you home tonight.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bay was violet. Traffic was thick. André shifted in his seat and checked his phone.  The green light kept flashing. Broken, he thought as he scrolled, seeing no new messages. His mouth was dry; his tongue like paper. The engine continued to whir. Nobody seemed to notice his shirt. In dull red letters it read, “6th Annual MS Fish Taco Challenge Champ.” The flailing fish below received his smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caras&quot;&gt;Cara’s&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Finally,” said Cara as André entered her small, downtown Oakland apartment. He removed his sturdy Columbia hiking books, worn from overuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s a bit of a hike. You have to take…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We need to talk,” Cara interrupted. She had her way of doing it nicely, but André suspected the tone to be masking some greater ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microwave beeped.Once. Twice. Cara was there to stop the third. The small apartment filled with the smell of melted, microwave cheese on corn flour tortilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why do you do this?” Cara pleaded as she removed a jar of salsa from the new refrigerator, void of doodles and magnets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It pays.  It’s more than I could make…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s not about that,” she interrupted. “I just, if we’re getting married, it seems I ought to know why. Is this who you are, or… what’s so important about it? MS?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;André looked down at his shirt. The truth was that he knew next to nothing about MS. He knew next to nothing about half the places he went to compete, or the charities sponsoring the events. What he did know about, deep down, was how at home he felt, guiding timeless creations from plate to mouth, one after another with balletic indulgence, peaking out from behind messy fingers at the curious kids and irreverent fathers who came to watch the absurd caloric carnivals that André called his sport. He knew his talent appeared semi-supernatural to the more common appetites of his spellbound spectators. And it felt good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I do like to do these, Cara. It’s my thing. People have all kinds of weird things they like to do, and this feels good to me. Like I was meant to be up there and make that kind of fun for people. I have a real shot next month at Nathan’s.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s a tremendous waste of food. And bad for you. I know you like it and it makes people happy, but… I don’t know… like how you could make this such a focus and all that. I don’t see it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe you don’t have to” said André. “I’d like you to, but maybe you don’t have to.” He began a slow walk toward her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s more that I feel like people find meaning in what they do. Or that they should or something like that,” said Cara as she finished her quesadilla. André drew nearer to her in the kitchen. His eyes traced her extended arm as it reached for the faucet. The water came out fast, pounding hard against the empty sink. He paused, then reached for her other wrist, holding it delicately. She turned and gave him a drawn out look. They kissed. Cara bowed her head. André felt her soft brown hair, poking from the back of a mesh, white hat the way it so often did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;André zoomed out, “I’m missing a lot, meaning-wise and all that. Mostly about
you. Can you answer this sorta thing? You can, and I’m afraid I’m in the dark
about what you’d say. Eating with a blindfold.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moon was barely visible from the window above the sink. The city lights dimmed the stars against the sky. André and Cara were silent, standing together as if assigned, placed beside each other on two square tiles in a rectangular kitchen in a prism apartment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nathans&quot;&gt;Nathan’s&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcer gave the words of institution, blessing each body with praise. “The three foot noodle eating, cannoli eating, chicken tender eating champion of the world: Karl, “The Crusher,” Kotlowski!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applause swelled louder with each new contestant. Seasoned spectators knew
André was a favorite by the order he was introduced, followed only by last year’s
champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aaaaaandrrrrréééé… Eats! Ladies and gentlemen.” He took his place on the far end of the stage where the likes of Takeru Kobayashi, Joey Chestnut, and Matt Stonie once stood. He was among the best that day, a rising star with a bid for first, predicted to at least make a top three finish. What separated the top three finishers from the rest of the pack was often a fifteen-dog difference. André was the product of dedication, a symbol to fans and eaters alike, and today his sights were set. The defending champ sauntered onto the stage. The announcer spoke the words of intinction. The dogs came out, then the judges for each contestant. The clock began to tick. Then all was a blur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andrés&quot;&gt;André’s&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;André’s breaths were quick. Two at a time he grabbed and shoved. The hot dogs
were good at first. Then better. Then slowly, surely, with glances to the right and left,
every so often, they tasted worse and worse. They were boulders, rising, falling. Until
finally he pushed without sensation, numb to the results. But it was when he saw the
number beside him, signaling his four dog deficit, that try as he did to conquer four in
one grab, he couldn’t, looking instead to the people below, loud and waving, all heads to
the sky but one. This, a bowed, hatted head, white mesh with soft brown hair. He did not
know what made it rise and fall, but he was determined to discover; to two at a time
digest the dissonance of the sounds in this place and many others; to carry each other
through.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 05:03:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/short-stories/dogs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/short-stories/dogs/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Short-Stories</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Grasping What We Cannot Grasp</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A Walk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eyes already touch the sunny hill.&lt;br /&gt;
Going far ahead of the road I have begun.&lt;br /&gt;
So we are grasped by what we cannot grasp;&lt;br /&gt;
It has inner light, even from a distance–&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And charges us, even if we do not reach it,&lt;br /&gt;
Into something else, which, hardly sensing it,&lt;br /&gt;
We already are; a gesture waves us on&lt;br /&gt;
Answering our own wave…&lt;br /&gt;
But what we feel is the wind in our faces.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Rainer Rilke (&lt;a href=&quot;https://allpoetry.com/A-Walk&quot;&gt;All Poetry&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cartesian Ideas and Sentiments in “A Walk” by Rainer Rilke&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the first modern philosopher, René Descartes has been informing our thoughts and sentiments since the beginning of the 17th century.  Rainer Rilke was a poet who wrote during the late 19th and early 20th century.  His poem “A Walk,” while perhaps not written with the intention of expressing Cartesian ideas, is informed by the ideas of Descartes, as Descartes’ ideas drastically shape the way we look at questions of doubting and knowing.  Rilke’s poem depicts a human relationship with truth, Descartes’ central concern in his writings from both &lt;em&gt;Discourse on Method&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Meditations on First Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Descartes’ method for achieving truth begins where Rilke’s eyes begin in “A Walk.”  Both men “beyond the road…” “…have begun.”  Descartes knows what he is looking for.  He wants something on which his eyes can rest, and his eyes do not rest anywhere except for on the truth that he has yet to find, as he begins his quest toward certainty.  This initial comparison is likely not because Rilke was informed by a Cartesian idea, but it provides the grounds for the Cartesian idea that is a central sentiment on the walk of Rainer Rilke: “We are grasped by what we cannot grasp.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are grasped by the notion of perfection, of something true, of something perfect.  Descartes himself is the best example of this, but more significantly, it is in our doubting of what we know – in our failure to grasp – that we know anything at all: that we think and as such know we exist.  Even if we are afflicted by our inability to grasp truth, to hold something tightly to us or reverently above us, we still are grasped with this very notion of the capacity to know or not know and the understanding of this phenomenon.  Rilke says that what we grasp “has inner light.”  It is in itself true.  In &lt;em&gt;Discourse on Method&lt;/em&gt; Descartes writes that “I am, I exist” is necessarily true in the very act of his stating it or thinking it.  It is as if he just feels it; as if he shouts it because the shouting makes it pierce all the louder as true.  Descartes finds truth in his own being by the impossibility of the contrary, because in the very act of contemplating his being, his being is true, even if truth appears beyond him, like the light of Rilke that shines “even from a distance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another Cartesian idea informing Rilke’s poem is the notion of an innate idea “charging” us.  In writing about the inner light Rilke finds on his walk, this light that charges us, Rilke refers to the function of charging.  Charging enables, it allows something else, some goal, some sort of truth.  In proving the existence of God, the greatest of all possible lights in the eyes of many, Descartes writes both of how the idea of God is an innate idea, an inner light, and also about how this idea is like a charge, empowering us to know and live.  Descartes advocates that the only way we, as imperfect creatures, finite and flawed, can know of God, is if a conception of the infinite has been given to us by something infinite, this being God.  It follows that the only way we can know of anything else, of the finite substances in the physical world we sense, is if God has enabled us to do so.  God charges us with the ability to sense and know, because otherwise, we could not be certain as to whether or not the way reality appears is deceptive, and we could not achieve true knowledge because we would have this constant doubt.  With God as an inner light, our conceptions are informed and our perceptions remain true as long as we do not waver from God.  Descartes warns, however, that even though a perfect God does not himself deceive us, we can still deceive ourselves, or more likely fail to sense our accidental self-deceit or live unaware of what is actually true.  This leads to another Cartesian idea Rilke employs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not only charged according to Rilke’s poem by some inner light, but also charged to be something new, with the catch that we already are this thing.  It is, as Rilke says, something we barely sense.  This state of being something we are already equipped to be follows a Cartesian notion.  It is a paradox upon first glance, as Descartes writes that God, being perfect and undeceiving, has not given us faculties that would allow us to make mistakes, and we should not make mistakes by this line of thought.  Yet, we, being human, are flawed.  In this way, we, according to Descartes, make false judgments as to the nature of truth, requiring us to put trust in God that the way things are, and the way we are, is correct because it proceeds from God.  In &lt;em&gt;Meditations on First Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; Descartes writes, “No doubt God could have created me such that I never erred.  No doubt, again, God always wills what is best.  Is it better that I should be in error rather than not?”  Because God is perfect, Descartes goes on to note that the state of human imperfection holds a perfect place in the universe that is, itself, perfect and where the imperfections of unique things are only pieces of the composite perfection that God has created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is that Rilke’s idea of finding truth in what we already are is a Cartesian notion, because what we already are is perfect, as it is what we are by God in the following way.  Descartes advocates that we are thinking things, and at this, things that reach, things that seek to grasp as Rilke writes, but we grasp only the substance that we are things who look beyond ourselves, seeing perfection, the infinite, God, only to remain ourselves, imperfect, human; yet, never ceasing to grasp at what we cannot grasp: eternity, perfection, all things divine and true beyond our trembling fingers and feeble conceptions.  This is our lot, to be thinking, grasping things.  This is our piece, small but even if incomplete, still existing amidst all things created to be perfect, and perfect in the composite case of the universe created by God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not clear if Rilke’s poem as it refers to grasping truth and being charged by an inner light is referring to God as Descartes might advocate, but we can conjecture that Rilke is referring to truth as something we struggle to know.  It is a struggle with the wind in our faces, but it is in our relationship with this struggle that the truth beckons us with a wave that answers our waves, illuminating the state of being that is our own, the state in which we are perfect as thinking, grasping things, with feet bound to the road, but eyes far ahead, narrowed to bear the wind, and touching nonetheless the sunny hill in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/grasping-what-we-cannot-grasp/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/poetry/grasping-what-we-cannot-grasp/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Poetry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Is this thing on?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 06:30:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/random/hello-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seafood-homer/random/hello-world/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Random</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
